{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In 2009, this country underwent the “Pots and Pans Revolution,” a series of protests against Geir Haarde. This country planned to nationalize Glitnir, one of three banks that ultimately defaulted in 2008. During that financial crisis, the IMF gave this country a 5 billion dollar bailout to stabilize the kr´ona. For ten points, name this European country where mass protests took place outside the Althing in Reykjavik [rek-ya-vik].",
      "answer": "Iceland"
    },
    {
      "question": "To plan this event, Richard Bissell reformed a “Special Group” of advisers known as the 5412 Committee. This event enraged one leader to the point of wanting to “splinter [its organizer] into a thousand pieces and scatter it into the winds;” seven months later, Allen Dulles was ultimately forced to resign. This event was carried out by the Brigade 2506 and prompted one side to formally ally with the Soviet Union. For ten points, name this 1961 event in which the CIA attempted to overthrow Fidel Castro by landing armed troops at a namesake bay.",
      "answer": [
        "Bay of Pigs invasion",
        "Playa Giron invasion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After this man’s travels were abruptly ended by World War I, he returned to composing and produced The Wooden Prince. This man included the movement “the Fatherland is in danger” and multiple refrains of “God save Franz the Kaiser” in a work about an Austrian invasion, Kossuth. He was asked by Miklos Horthy to remove the name of Bela Balazs from his most famous work, which is about the namesake duke’s fourth wife, Judith. For ten points, name this Hungarian composer of Duke Bluebeard’s Castle.",
      "answer": "Bela Bartok"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man began his writing career after facing exile following the fall of Amphipolis. In one work by this man, a winning army’s diplomats state that “the strong do what they can and the weak suffer what they must.” This man’s most famous work includes the Melian Dialogue and recounts how the Delian League was led into war against Sparta. Pericles’ Funeral Oration was recorded by, for ten points, what ancient Greek historian and author of a History of the Peloponnesian War?",
      "answer": "Thucydides"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1817, Thomas Gallaudet founded a school which standardized these languages in the USA in Hartford, Connecticut. A language of this type spontaneously arose in a school in Nicaragua in the early 1980s, and a language of this type arose in Martha’s Vineyard due to a hereditary disorder prevalent on the island. For ten points, name this type of language which uses manual and other visible body movements rather than through speech, primarily used by deaf people.",
      "answer": "Sign Languages"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man gave the unpopular George Herriman a lifetime contract in exchange for producing the comic strip Krazy Kat, and he poached another cartoonist, Richard Outcault, from a rival to secure the rights to “The Yellow Kid” comic. This man allegedly told Frederic Remington to “furnish the photos” so he could furnish the Spanish-American War. For ten points, name this publisher of the New York Journal, a rival of Joseph Pulitzer during the Spanish-American War.",
      "answer": "William Randolph Hearst"
    },
    {
      "question": "During World War II, this state’s leader allegedly kept a jar of eyeballs on his desk. This state was home to the infamous Jasenovac [YAH-sen-oh-vatz] concentration camp, where an estimated 20,000 Jews were killed. This state, whose flag featured a grenade against a white and red checker background, was led by a dictator with the title of Poglavnik, a translation of Fuhrer into this state’s Slavic language; that leader, Ante Pavelic, was the leader of the Ustashe party, which murdered an estimated half million Orthodox Christian Serbs. For ten points, name this Yugoslav republic with capital Zagreb.",
      "answer": "Croatia"
    },
    {
      "question": "A battle at this location resulted in the deaths of William Miller and Harold Stites and included a mortar attack ordered by James Johnston. Three residents of this location stole 50 raincoats to make an impromptu raft with the goal of reaching nearby Angel Island. Robert Stroud was labeled the “Birdman” of this location, where Al Capone was stabbed while incarcerated. For ten points, name this “inescapable” prison located in San Francisco Bay.",
      "answer": "Alcatraz Federal Penitentiary"
    },
    {
      "question": "This woman’s daughter, Susanna Cole, was the sole survivor of a raid on her family’s Pelham Bay settlement. Supporters of this woman created the Portsmouth Compact as part of creating a colony run by “judge” William Coddington. In the aftermath of one event, Roger Williams advised this woman to purchase land from the Narragansett natives. John Winthrop exiled this woman as part of the Antinomian Controversy. For ten points, name this woman who was expelled from the Massachusetts Bay Colony and helped found Rhode Island.",
      "answer": [
        "Anne Hutchinson",
        "Anne Marbury"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler established a detention camp for political opponents on Quiriquina Island. This leader’s rise to power was assisted by propaganda run by the newspapers La Tercera and El Murcurio. A deputy of this leader, Manuel Contreras, was sentenced to extensive prison time for using the DINA secret police to assassinate dissident Orlando Letellier. This man orchestrated a coup that deposed Salvador Allende in 1973. For ten points, name this right-wing dictator of Chile.",
      "answer": "Augusto Pinochet"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Rosenwald Fund was created to honor this man who, many years earlier, had been placed in charge of an Alabama institution by Samuel C. Armstrong. This man urged his followers to “cast down your bucket where you are” in an 1895 speech. This man was labeled the “Great Accommodator” by his rival for his belief that African Americans should cooperate with supportive whites, rather than take more radical actions. For ten points, name this long-time opponent of W.E.B. DuBois who established the Tuskegee Institute.",
        "answer": "Booker Taliaferro Washington"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Booker T. Washington’s “cast down your bucket” metaphor was used in a speech at the 1895 Cotton States and International Exposition in this city. Washington’s theories thus became known as this city’s Compromise.",
        "answer": "Atlanta"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a movie set during this war, a man authorizes a pig farm as a site for his experiments to resurrect the extinct aurochs. Jessica Chastain portrayed Antonina in a 2017 movie set during this war, The Zookeeper’s Wife. In another movie set during this war, Liam Neeson played a businessman who establishes an enamel factory in Krakow and who saves 850 people by transporting them to his new munitions factory. For ten points, name this setting of Schindler’s List.",
        "answer": "World War II"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Schindler’s List, this actor portrayed SS officer Amon G¨oth, who ran the Plaszow [plash-ov] concentration camp. His other historical roles include Charles Van Doren in Quiz Show, and his non- historical roles include Voldemort in the Harry Potter franchise.",
        "answer": "Ralph Fiennes , but be lenient"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, the Huks were a Communist guerrilla group that Edward Lansdale was tasked with putting down. The Moro Islamic Liberation Front also fought this country’s government. In 1983, a president of this country had an opposition leader assassinated at an airport and was married to a woman famous for her large collection of shoes. Ferdinand Marcos led, for ten points, what Asian country home to the islands of Luzon and Mindanao?",
        "answer": [
          "the Philippines",
          "Republika ng Pilipinas"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2012, this President of the Philippines reached a peace deal with the Moro Islamic Liberation Front. This politician, the son of the aforementioned assassinated leader, was succeeded by Rodrigo Duterte in 2016.",
        "answer": "Benigno Aquino III"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Treaty of Bromesbro brought an end to a stage of this war that was known as the Lennart Torstenson War. The Battle of Dessau Bridge took place in this war, which Denmark withdrew from via the Treaty of Lubeck. This war’s first major battle ended with a victory for Count Tilly at White Mountain. Axel Oxenstierna guided Sweden through this war after the Battle of Lutzen, where Gustavus Adolphus was slain. The Peace of Westphalia ended, for ten points, what 17th century war between Catholics and Protestants?",
        "answer": "Thirty Years War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Bohemian nobleman lost the Battle of Lutzen and was assassinated two years later by political rivals upset that he was seeking peace with Sweden.",
        "answer": [
          "Albrecht von Wallenstein",
          "von Waldstein"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This artist used a birds-eye view to show a road winding through a Massachusetts town in bright moonlight in his depiction of The Midnight Ride of Paul Revere. Three elderly women stand in front of a reproduction of Washington Crossing the Delaware in his painting Daughters of Revolution. This artist used his sister and his dentist as models in his painting in which a man holds a pitchfork in his right hand. For ten points, name this artist of American Gothic.",
        "answer": "Grant Wood"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "American Gothic was inspired by a farmhouse in Eldon in this U.S. state, where Grant Wood was born and raised.",
        "answer": "Iowa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One side in this battle launched an unsuccessful attack on “Eagle Day.” Keith Park and Hugh Dowding were key commanders for the defending side in this battle. A speech delivered during this battle declared that “Never in the field of human conflict was so much owed by so many to so few.” This battle prevented Operation Sea Lion from being carried out. Hurricanes and Spitfires were the most useful weapons for the R.A.F. in, for ten points, what 1940 aerial battle in which Germany’s Luftwaffe was defeated by the namesake country?",
        "answer": "Battle of Britain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The nearest inhabited islands to Easter Island are the Juan Fernandez Islands, themselves over 400 miles from Chile. In 1704, this Scottish privateer was marooned on one of the Juan Fernandez Islands, inspiring the story of Robinson Crusoe.",
        "answer": "Alexander Selkirk"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This project was conceived in the Canandaigua debtor prison by Jesse Hawley, who was looking to boost the grain industry. The ship Seneca Chief brought water that Samuel Wilkeson poured into a lake at the completion of this project. Because it had the support of the governor, this project was known as that man’s “Big Ditch.” Albany was connected through the Niagara Escarpment to Buffalo by, for ten points, what waterway that was completed in 1825 to help link New York with the Great Lakes?",
        "answer": "Erie Canal"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This politician pushed for the construction of his “Big Ditch” in his capacity as New York mayor, then as Federalist candidate in the 1812 election, and finally as Governor of New York.",
        "answer": "DeWitt Clinton"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Abraham Lincoln’s Political Career",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Decree issued by Lincoln on New Year’s Day 1863 freeing slaves in occupied Confederate territory.",
          "answer": "Emancipation Proclamation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amendment to the constitution permanently banning slavery, passed during Lincoln’s term.",
          "answer": "13th Amendment to the US Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "Federal holiday created by Lincoln; it was moved to its current date of the fourth Thursday in November much later.",
          "answer": "Thanksgiving Day"
        },
        {
          "question": "Legal writ whose suspension by Lincoln allowed suspects to be held without being informed of the charges against them.",
          "answer": "writ of habeas corpus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern Democratic candidate in the 1860 election, a longtime rival of Lincoln in Illinois politics.",
          "answer": "Stephen A. Douglas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Maine politician who served as Lincoln’s first Vice President.",
          "answer": "Hannibal Hamlin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Series of demands issued by Lincoln in the leadup to the Mexican-American War regarding the exact location where American blood was spilled.",
          "answer": "Spot Resolutions"
        },
        {
          "question": "Copperhead politician from Ohio who was arrested for criticizing “King Lincoln” and exiled to the Confederacy.",
          "answer": "Clement Vallandigham The Gallic Wars"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Considering the first century BC wars in Gaul, name the...",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about Considering the first century BC wars in Gaul, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country south of Belgium that was the site of the wars.",
          "answer": "France"
        },
        {
          "question": "River that marked the border of Gaul, and later, the Roman Empire.",
          "answer": "Rhine River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mountain range that separated Gaul into Cis and Trans provinces before its conquest.",
          "answer": [
            "Alps",
            "Cisalpine and/or Transalpine Gaul"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman general who recorded his conquest of Gaul in Commentaries.",
          "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arverni general who led a major uprising against Roman rule, marked by a victory at the Battle of Gergovia.",
          "answer": "Vercingetorix"
        },
        {
          "question": "City surrounded by two walls by the Romans in 52 BC, marking one end of the Gallic resistance.",
          "answer": "Alesia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman legion that was “mounted” by its commander during the war.",
          "answer": "Tenth Legion or Legio X Equestris"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conference that continued the Gallic Wars and gave Crassus command in Syria.",
          "answer": "Lucca Conference"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "African Cities",
      "prompt": "Name the city where...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nelson Mandela’s memorial service was held, the most populous city in South Africa.",
          "answer": "Johannesburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "The University of Sankore was built, an ancient city with a reputation of being very hard to find.",
          "answer": "Timbuktu"
        },
        {
          "question": "A 1943 Allied conference was held and a classic 1942 film was set.",
          "answer": "Casablanca"
        },
        {
          "question": "The USS Philadelphia was burned in 1803.",
          "answer": "Tripoli"
        },
        {
          "question": "The US embassy in Kenya was bombed in 1998.",
          "answer": "Nairobi"
        },
        {
          "question": "A US embassy was bombed at the same time as the Kenya attack, even though it was replaced as capital by Dodoma.",
          "answer": "Dar es Salaam"
        },
        {
          "question": "Riots in 1948 led to the arrest of Kwame Nkrumah and the “Big Six,” sparking an independence movement.",
          "answer": "Accra"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muammar Gaddafi was born in 1942 and killed in 2011.",
          "answer": "Sirte"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One king of this name prohibited his wife from attending his own coronation, then introduced the Pains and Penalties Bill to annul his marriage to Caroline of Brunswick. While serving kings of this name, (20 pts)",
        "Spencer Perceval was assassinated and Robert Walpole became Britain’s de facto first Prime Minister. (10 pts)",
        "Porphyria [por-feer-ee-uh] was blamed for the mental illness of a king of this name. For ten points, give this British royal name whose third holder received the Olive Branch Petition from the American colonists."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George",
        "George IV throughout",
        "George III starting at “Spencer",
        "”",
        "George I",
        "II starting at “Robert”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Bly was hanged for looting during this event, but most of its participants were pardoned or given amnesty. Militiamen refused to fight for governor James (20 pts)",
        "Bowdoin as he attempted to disperse protests in front of courts in Northampton and Worcester. The (10 pts)",
        "federal government failed to pay for an army to end this event, a rebel seizure of the Springfield Armory. For ten points, name this 1787 rebellion of disgruntled farmers in Massachusetts that highlighted the weakness of the Articles of Confederation."
      ],
      "answer": "Shays’ Rebellion or Uprising, etc."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This mathematician proved that every Riemannian manifold can be embedded into some Euclidean space. This man, who once gave a presentation to the American Mathematical Society in which he claimed to have solved the Riemann hypothesis, was (20 pts)",
        "killed with his wife in a taxi accident after receiving the Abel prize in 2015. The 1994 Nobel for Economics was awarded to this man for his work in (10 pts)",
        "game theory, specifically the introduction of his namesake equilibrium. For ten points, name this mathematician whose struggle with schizophrenia was portrayed in the film A Beautiful Mind."
      ],
      "answer": "John Forbes Nash"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A precolonial state based in this modern country was founded by Usman dan Fodio. Another precolonial state in this country was ruled by kings called obas and was famed for its bronze work. This country’s (20 pts)",
        "Sokoto caliphate was founded by its Fulani people, and before colonization, this country’s (10 pts)",
        "Yoruba and Ibo people largely lived in decentralized confederations. For ten points, name this country where the port of Lagos was a center of the slave trade."
      ],
      "answer": "Nigeria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A lynch mob in this state tortured Claude Neal in 1934. On Election Day 1920 in this state’s town of Ocoee, whites killed over 50 African Americans and drove out the rest of the black population. The 1923 Rosewood massacre took place in this state, where the (20 pts)",
        "NAACP’s Harry Moore and his wife were killed by a KKK bombing in 1950. In 2012, police in the city of (10 pts)",
        "Sanford were criticized for not promptly arresting George Zimmerman, who shot and killed an unarmed black teenager. For ten points, name this state where Trayvon Martin was killed in a suburb north of Orlando."
      ],
      "answer": "Florida"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A poem about this man ends “In the prison of his days / Teach the free man how to praise,” and references how “In the nightmare of the dark / All the dogs of Europe bark.” After claiming that a certain author’s work “stirred [his] (20 pts)",
        "blood,” this man used the line “They seek not for hidden treasures, they know not how to cast nets” in his introduction to Tagore’s Gitanjali. This man, who “disappeared in the dead of winter” but died on a (10 pts)",
        "“dark cold day” in a W.H. Auden eulogy, declared “A terrible beauty is born” at the end of a poem about a failed uprising against the British. For ten points, name this Irish poet of “Easter, 1916.”"
      ],
      "answer": "William Butler Yeats"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This speech revealed that accusations against the Mingrelian organization had been completely fabricated. This speech uses an analogy in which the speaker Kossior suddenly stopped appearing on Radio Kiev to warn against hastily removing (20 pts)",
        "names from monuments. This speech, which was ordered to be read to all Konsomol meetings, marked the beginning of its author’s namesake political “thaw.” The (10 pts)",
        "Cult of Personality and its Consequences” was the official title of, for ten points, what 1956 speech by Nikita Khrushchev that denounced Stalin?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nikita Khrushchev’s Secret Speech",
        "On the Cult of Personality and its Consequences before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This history of this country was documented by Jesuit missionary Pedro Paez. The Nine Saints spread Christianity throughout this nation, which houses the Garima Gospels, an illuminated ancient manuscript. This country’s city of (20 pts)",
        "Lalibela is home to eleven churches carved from rock. In this country, King Ezana was baptized by Frumentius, who converted people in its kingdom of (10 pts)",
        "Aksum. The Solomonic dynasty, which claimed descent from the biblical Queen of Sheba, used to rule this nation. For ten points, name this African nation with capital at Addis Ababa."
      ],
      "answer": "Ethiopia"
    }
  ]
}